<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: datafist | Quantified Savagery]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/datafist/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T00:48:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Evan Savage]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[datafist: Exploration And Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/12/21/datafist-exploration-and-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/12/21/datafist-exploration-and-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I introduce datafist, an in-browser tool for visually exploring
your data. </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="first-a-quote">First, A Quote</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Are we analyzing data? Then we should be manipulating the data themselves; or if we are designing an analysis of data, we should be manipulating the analytic structures themselves.</p><footer><strong>Direct Manipulation Interfaces</strong> <cite><a href='http://cleo.ics.uci.edu/teaching/Winter10/231/readings/1-HutchinsHollanNorman-DirectManipulation-HCI.pdf'>cleo.ics.uci.edu/teaching/231/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2 id="the-sixfold-path-of-self-tracking">The Sixfold Path Of Self-Tracking</h2>

<p>Self-tracking is a complex process. It can be broken down into stages:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Intent:</em> our initial goals or motivations in deciding to self-track.</li>
  <li><em>Tools:</em> the devices or methods we use for tracking.</li>
  <li><em>Measurement:</em> collecting our data using those tools.</li>
  <li><em>Analysis:</em> extracting insights from our data.</li>
  <li><em>Interpretation:</em> creating personal meaning from those insights.</li>
  <li><em>Action:</em> responding to that personal meaning.</li>
</ul>

<p>Thanks to smartphones and cheap sensors, many of us already have the tools
necessary for measurement. The psychology of intent and action is rapidly
being explored through <a href="http://www.meetup.com/habitdesign/">Habit Design</a> and <a href="http://captology.stanford.edu/">Captology</a>, with
startups like <a href="http://lift.do/">Lift</a> and <a href="https://www.beeminder.com/">Beeminder</a> harnessing the findings
to great effect.</p>

<p><em>What are the technologies of analysis and interpretation?</em></p>

<h3 id="visualization">Visualization</h3>

<p>Visualizations, even interactive ones, are usually designed to <em>answer
specific questions</em> such as <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2012/11/07/us/politics/obamas-diverse-base-of-support.html">how did Obama win re-election?</a>
Within the context of those questions, they help us understand our data
intuitively. Outside that context, however, they are often useless.</p>

<h3 id="statisticalmathematical-software">Statistical/Mathematical Software</h3>

<p>Environments like <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R</a> and <a href="http://www.wolfram.com/mathematica/">Mathematica</a> allow you to <em>explore
your data in meticulous detail.</em> In the hands of people like
<a href="http://blog.stephenwolfram.com/2012/03/the-personal-analytics-of-my-life/">Stephen Wolfram</a>, they are the holy grail of data analysis. For the
less technically inclined, they remain hopelessly unintuitive.</p>

<h2 id="a-middle-road">A Middle Road</h2>

<p>What we need is <em>something between the two</em>, a hybrid that exposes the
exploratory power of the latter through the intuitive interface of the former.
Such a tool would give us the opportunity to <em>explore our data as we see fit.</em>
We could ask our data questions, iterating quickly on those questions until
we reach useful insights.</p>

<p>Until we can all converse with our data with the fluency of <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_the_good_news_of_the_decade.html">Hans Rosling</a>,
there’s still room for improvement!</p>

<h2 id="datafist">datafist</h2>

<p>datafist tries to bridge this gap by providing <em>visual and gestural actions</em>
for data manipulation. This is probably easier to demonstrate than describe,
so here’s a screencast that shows an early development version of datafist
in action:</p>

<div>
  <iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/ypitHPXKa8M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p>As you use datafist, <em>you’re constantly modifying the analysis itself.</em>
This modification takes place through <em>visual and gestural actions:</em> you
move channels to the viewer, drag out ranges of time to zoom in on, and draw
regions around interesting clusters. As you do this, the view is
<em>updated in real-time</em>, allowing you to see the effects of your actions.</p>

<h3 id="try-datafist-out">Try datafist Out!</h3>

<p>I’m hosting a version of datafist <a href="http://datafist.savageevan.com">here at savageevan.com</a>.
Note that this is still a very early development version!</p>

<h3 id="contribute-to-datafist">Contribute to datafist!</h3>

<p>If you’re interested in making datafist better, <a href="https://github.com/candu/datafist">fork me on github!</a>
Bug reports should be submitted <a href="https://github.com/candu/datafist/issues">via the issue tracker</a>.
In particular, if you have a CSV file that won’t import properly, please attach
it for testing purposes!</p>

<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.audiomulch.com/">AudioMulch</a> is an awesome graphical audio synthesis tool.</li>
  <li><a href="http://puredata.info/">PureData</a> and <a href="http://cycling74.com/products/max/">Max/MSP</a> are visual signal processing languages.</li>
  <li><a href="http://cleo.ics.uci.edu/teaching/Winter10/231/readings/1-HutchinsHollanNorman-DirectManipulation-HCI.pdf">Direct Manipulation Interfaces</a> is a classic paper on the design of
natural-seeming interfaces. You’ll recognize some of the interface concepts
from the analysis package design mocks at the beginning.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.startuplessonslearned.com/2011/11/startup-is-vision.html">FAKEGRIMLOCK</a> is a fountain of poorly-Englished wisdom on
entrepreneurship.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
