<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Text Processing | Quantified Savagery]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/text-processing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T14:27:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Evan Savage]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Tale of Two Trips]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2013/10/09/a-tale-of-two-trips/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T09:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2013/10/09/a-tale-of-two-trips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This summer, <a href="http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/~valkyrie/">Valkyrie</a> and I travelled
through Eastern Asia.  We started with the Great Barrier Reef and rainforests near
Cairns, then went onwards to Singapore, Vietnam, Cambodia, Malaysia, and Korea
before spending three typhoon-stricken days holed up in Manila, Philippines.</p>

<p>As with our <a href="http://fearlesstost.github.io/biketotheearth/">bike trip</a>, we kept
a <a href="http://ramblelust.savageinter.net/">daily journal</a> of our travels in blog
form.  In this post, I visualize the two trips from our blog entries using some
simple word count graphs.  These aren’t the most sophisticated visualizations
possible, but they provide a simple starting point to build upon in future
blog posts.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>First of all, it feels good to write another post!  The rapidly upcoming <a href="http://quantifiedself.com/conference/San-Francisco-2013/">Quantified Self 2013 Global Conference</a>
seemed like a good excuse to break seven months of blog neglect, so here I am.</p>

<p>I’ll refer to these trips as <em>Bike to the Earth</em> and <em>Ramblelust</em> respectively,
following the names of each trip blog.  Let’s start with a look at the broadest
of broad textual measures, word count.</p>

<h2 id="word-count">Word Count</h2>

<p>How many words did we write for each trip?  How many per post, on average?</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ python global_word_count.py &lt; BikeToTheEarth/posts_normalized.json 
</span><span class='line'>141329 words in 197 posts (717 words/post)&lt;/p>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p>$ python global_word_count.py &lt; Ramblelust/posts_normalized.json 
</span><span class='line'>61010 words in 86 posts (709 words/post)</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Not much difference here.  What happens if we graph the word counts over time?
Top is Bike to the Earth, bottom is Ramblelust.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5Sv5_JZEDdw/UlcoazZGSxI/AAAAAAAAAks/9TZH7nDzpnQ/w1000/biketotheearth_daily_words.jpg">
<img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-BW5K-iWb56c/UlcoZ4fktZI/AAAAAAAAAkw/3g2w4bbbMtI/w1000/ramblelust_daily_words.jpg"></p>

<p>One point jumps out on the Bike to the Earth graph: <a href="http://fearlesstost.github.io/biketotheearth/posts/2010/10/19/hellbania.html">this post</a>,
a massive 3600-word whopper that details our arduous exit from the rain-stricken
Albanian coastline and into Greece.  For comparison, our longest post from
Ramblelust was <a href="http://ramblelust.savageinter.net/blog/2013/06/29/cam-ranh-ing-around/">this one</a>
about our CouchSurfing experiences in Cam Ranh, a short distance south from
Nha Trang along the Vietnamese coast.</p>

<p>Still, it’s hard to make much out of such noisy data.  Let’s smooth that a bit
by looking at weekly averages. Again, top is Bike to the Earth, bottom is Ramblelust.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9YT2XueNpAs/UlcodH_CpwI/AAAAAAAAAkk/0ZnCYmXSMJc/w1000/biketotheearth_daily_words_smoothed.jpg">
<img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-C-Q604GWq84/UlcoesNibrI/AAAAAAAAAjk/8RHMmaBdOi0/w1000/ramblelust_daily_words_smoothed.jpg"></p>

<p>Now another pattern pops out of the Bike to the Earth data: sometime around
the beginning of September, our writing output doubled.  At that time, we were
just entering Italy, where we were sandwiched in between the southern Alps
and the sea for about 900km before reaching Rome.</p>

<p>As I go through this process, I’m constantly jumping back and forth between
the blog posts and these graphs.  As with all visualization, this context is an
essential part of understanding the data.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>

<p>There are lots of places we could go from here:</p>

<ul>
  <li>sentiment analysis;</li>
  <li>location-based visualization (by combining with country data);</li>
  <li>authorship analysis (my posts vs. Valkyrie’s posts)…</li>
</ul>

<p>…the list goes on.  What would you like to see?  Comment via Facebook or
Twitter to let me know, and I’ll put it into the next blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
