<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thoughts | Quantified Savagery]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-13T15:24:45-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Evan Savage]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Healthy Isn't A Place You Go To]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/11/07/healthy-isnt-a-place-you-go-to/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-07T07:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/11/07/healthy-isnt-a-place-you-go-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I expand on some <a href="/blog/2012/10/02/welcome-to-quantified-savagery/">earlier thoughts</a> about the
nature and purpose of the <a href="http://quantifiedself.com/">Quantified Self movement</a>.
In looking at personal identity from a Quantified Self perspective, I argue
that self-tracking gives us a means for reclaiming control of that identity.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-revelation">The Revelation</h2>

<p>When I started down the philosophical path that ultimately led into the
Quantified Self vortex, it was with a simple question:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>How do we build game-like systems to improve our lives?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This isn’t a new question. The <a href="http://realityisbroken.org/">Reality Is Broken</a>
thesis has long since reached tech geek mantra-hood.
<a href="https://www.superbetter.com/">SuperBetter</a> and similar games have broken ground on the
concrete implications of that mantra.</p>

<p>Much more recently, during a walk home with <a href="http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/~valkyrie/">Valkyrie Savage</a>, I had
another thought:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Self-tracking makes self-expertise possible.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>We may self-track for a variety of reasons, including:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>addressing symptoms:</strong> perhaps I feel overweight, underslept, or stressed
out.</li>
  <li><strong>improving habits:</strong> perhaps I want to exercise more, drink less, or read
a book each month.</li>
  <li><strong>satisfying curiosity:</strong> perhaps I’m fascinated by data visualization,
psychology, or lifehacking.</li>
</ul>

<p>Whether data collection is your focus or merely an unintended side effect,
<em>this data makes it possible to know ourselves in new ways.</em> This
self-knowledge is different from expert other-knowledge.</p>

<h2 id="self-knowledge-and-other-knowledge">Self-Knowledge and Other-Knowledge</h2>

<p>Doctors are trained to recognize general patterns of the human body.
From a diagnosis perspective, your medical history is only interesting
insofar as it allows you to be grouped together with similar patients.
That grouping is a <em>pattern profile</em> in your doctor’s mind, and it informs their
<em>expert other-knowledge</em> of you.</p>

<p>By contrast, you have intimate <em>self-knowledge</em> of your body and its symptoms.
When do they occur? After eating which foods? In which locations?
How often? How severe? The doctor will often ask these more <em>technical
questions</em> to fill in the data missing from their patterns. There are,
however, important questions that are often either missed or left barely
explored:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>What do those symptoms cost you?</em> What do they prevent you from enjoying in
life? If you could solve one of them, which would it be?</li>
  <li>If they are preventable, <em>why do you continue the behavior that causes or
aggravates them?</em> What is the best way to get you to stop?</li>
  <li><em>How do these symptoms impact those around you?</em></li>
  <li>Do you really need medicine to deal with these symptoms? Could they be solved
with more sleep? More exercise? Healthier diet? <em>What is the least invasive
and costly means of addressing your issue?</em></li>
  <li>If you do need medicine, <em>how can you be convinced to take it?</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>This is not to say that experts are without value. In their current
incarnation, they fulfill much of the promise of the <a href="/blog/2012/10/02/welcome-to-quantified-savagery/">Quantified Mass</a>.
Their (hopefully) extensive training equips them with powerful insights
rooted in centuries of scientific inquiry.
Powerful as those insights are, however, <em>they are ill-suited to address 
more personal questions</em> in a way that is meaningful to you.</p>

<h2 id="personal-identity-and-place-ism">Personal Identity And Place-Ism</h2>

<p>I titled this post:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Healthy Isn’t A Place You Go To</p></blockquote></p>

<p>What do I mean by that? Consider these popular sentiments:</p>

<ul>
  <li>To become fit, I go to the gym.</li>
  <li>To get well, I go to the doctor.</li>
  <li>To learn, I go to school.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’d argue that a lifetime of handing over control of these personal questions
<em>conditions us to associate states of being</em> (fitness, wellness, learnedness)
<em>with places</em> (gym, doctor, school). Those states become mechanical attributes
devoid of identity, knobs we go elsewhere to have others tweak for us. For
lack of a better term, I’ll call this place-ism.</p>

<p>This isn’t just philosophical posturing. There is <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=behavior+change+and+identity">growing inquiry</a>
into the hypothesis that <a href="http://wayoftheduck.com/belief-change">behavior and belief change are linked</a>.
A number of theories, such as
<a href="http://www.selfdeterminationtheory.org/theory">self-determination theory</a> and the
<a href="http://www.uri.edu/research/cprc/TTM/detailedoverview.htm">Transtheoretical Model</a>,
have sprung up in an attempt to rigorously define these processes of change.</p>

<p>If that’s the
case, training ourselves to externalize behavior change can’t be good, as it
necessarily <em>reduces our capacity for belief change.</em></p>

<h2 id="beyond-place-ism">Beyond Place-Ism…</h2>

<p>Self-tracking allows us to <em>tie mechanical questions</em> - where? when? what?
how much? - <em>to personal questions</em> and vice-versa. Data help us
answer personal questions. Personal questions help us decide what 
data are needed to answer them. This cycle <em>makes us active participants in
our own lives.</em></p>

<p>What role do experts have in this cycle? The point is not to exclude them
entirely, but rather to <em>change their role from identity gatekeepers
identity consultants.</em> By treating them as consultants, you seek advice
of your own free will and with the understanding that some of it may not
be applicable to you. You decide what role the consultant plays in your
health, your education, your overall identity.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>What if learning were not a place, but a state of being?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<h2 id="and-back-to-gameplay">…And Back To Gameplay</h2>

<p>How are</p>

<p><blockquote><p>How do we build game-like systems to improve our lives?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>and</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Self-tracking makes self-expertise possible.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>related? <em>Self-expertise is the improvement.</em> It breaks place-ism, casts
self-knowledge and other-knowledge as complementary equals, and moves us
towards active participation. <em>Self-tracking is pervasive gameplay</em>, and
that’s awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Quantified Savagery]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/10/02/welcome-to-quantified-savagery/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-02T21:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/2012/10/02/welcome-to-quantified-savagery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m <a href="http://cv.savageevan.com/">Evan Savage</a> and I’d like to welcome you
to Quantified Savagery. I recently left my job at Facebook to focus on
exploring the
<a href="http://quantifiedself.com/">Quantified Self</a>,
and I’m super-excited to share those explorations here on my new blog.</p>

<p>In this first post, I’ll explain the Quantified Self, give you a sense of
what I’ll be posting in the near future, and provide some helpful tips on
reading this blog.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="what-is-the-quantified-self">What is the Quantified Self?</h2>

<p>I’ve had to explain this countless times to friends, family, and
co-workers: why did I leave
<a href="http://www.glassdoor.com/Reviews/Facebook-Reviews-E40772.htm">one of the world’s best employers</a>
to explore a field most people haven’t even heard of?
I usually start by name-dropping
<a href="http://www.fitbit.com/">Fitbit</a> or <a href="http://nikeplus.nike.com/plus/">Nike+</a> as
prominent examples of personal data collection and analysis. I then do some
semi-coherent hand-waving about the vast potential of data collection and
analysis. All of this is really just an attempt to cover up the fact
that <em>I don’t really know</em>.</p>

<p>That doesn’t really cut it as an explanation for a major life decision,
though, so let’s look a bit deeper.</p>

<p>The Quantified Self
<a href="http://quantifiedself.com/">community website</a> has this tagline:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>self knowledge through numbers</p></blockquote></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>self:</strong> you seek to answer <em>your</em> questions.</li>
  <li><strong>knowledge:</strong> in doing this, you gain an <em>awareness</em> of your behaviors and
motivations.</li>
  <li><strong>through numbers:</strong> this process is driven by <em>data</em> gathered from sensors,
journals, and any other tools at your disposal.</li>
</ul>

<p>This is a good first-level approximation: you <em>gather</em> your data, <em>analyze</em> it,
and <em>interpret</em> the analysis to become more <em>self-aware</em>.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>As I said before, though, this is only a first-level approximation. There are
two main ways in which Quantified Self can achieve greater awesomeness:
<em>Quantified Mass</em> and <em>Qualified Self</em>.</p>

<h3 id="quantified-mass">Quantified Mass</h3>

<p>As Gary Wolf pointed out in his
<a href="http://www.onthemedia.org/people/gary-wolf/">interview with On the Media</a>,
self-tracking doesn’t lead to self-obsession but rather to group-awareness.
In asking our own questions, we find that these questions are important to
others as well. When many people gather comparable datasets to answer the
same questions, there’s an opportunity to extract insights
that could benefit us all.</p>

<p>Scalable <em>mass</em> insights have massive power. Taking a 1% chunk out of the
American obesity epidemic might not sound impressive, but that’s potentially
a <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bethhoffman/2012/08/16/what-the-obesity-epidemic-costs-us-infographic/">$6 billion impact</a>
on direct and indirect costs. And that’s just in the United States, which
counts for a tiny slice of the global mobile userbase.</p>

<p>Many of the requisite data mining tools already
exist, but they’re being employed to increase advertising click-through rates
by 1%. The engineers building these tools aren’t indifferent to societal
problems; rather, <em>the datasets to solve those problems largely don’t exist yet.</em>
Once they do, the quantified mass can start driving these massive-scale
incremental wins.</p>

<h3 id="qualified-self">Qualified Self</h3>

<p><blockquote><p>Not everything that counts can be counted,<br/>and not everything that can be counted counts.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Our perception of life is rarely numerical. Much more often, it is visual,
auditory, tactile, or experiential. 
The problem with data is that you can’t
<a href="http://worrydream.com/#!/KillMath">see</a> or
<a href="http://blog.makezine.com/2009/02/08/haptic-compass/">feel</a> them.
Even the best data scientists use
data only as a means of
<a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/hans_rosling_shows_the_best_stats_you_ve_ever_seen.html">telling a story</a>.</p>

<p>Put another way, this awareness process starts with qualitative questions
and ends with qualitative answers. Data is the intermediate representation,
one we use for its unique ability to permit detailed analysis. Ultimately,
though, we’re going to ask questions like</p>

<p><blockquote><p>How can I improve my fitness?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>and expect answers like</p>

<p><blockquote><p>By finding training partners. By doing more engaging athletic<br/>activities. By setting aside regularly scheduled time.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>We’re going to need moral support. We’re going to give and receive advice.
We’re going to have conversations and <em>tell stories</em> about our personal
struggles with fitness.</p>

<p>These qualified aspects of self-awareness are arguably the most important
to us. <em>Data provide a stepping-stone</em>, something we can build upon
to address these aspects. By building systems designed for the qualified self,
we can bring the benefits of the quantified self to everyone.</p>

<h3 id="back-to-the-quantified-self">Back to the Quantified Self</h3>

<p>That sums up why I’m so excited about Quantified Self: there really is an
enormous potential here to revolutionize our lives on both the global/societal
and individual levels.
It’s also a fantastically diverse field, one that connects hackers and 
doctors and entrepreneurs and teachers and artists through mutual pursuit of
insanely lofty goals.</p>

<h2 id="upcoming-content">Upcoming Content</h2>

<p>The next few posts will detail my experiences <em>dealing with panic
disorder through self-tracking</em>. I gave a talk about this to the Bay Area
Quantified Self community, which you can
<a href="http://quantifiedself.com/2012/07/evan-savage-on-panic-tracking/">view here</a>
for some initial context.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-read-this-blog">How To Read This Blog</h2>

<p>Although this is a blog about personal data, one of my primary goals is to
make the thoughts and insights shared here accessible to a broad audience.
You can filter what you read with these categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/non-technical/" class="category">Non-Technical</a>:
expect to see insights, thoughts, discussions, descriptions
of planned experiments, and post-mortems. I might link to articles, studies,
or books that provide context, but I’ll try to summarize the relevant
parts.</li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/technical/" class="category">Technical</a>:
expect to see code, statistical analysis, $ \LaTeX $ formulae,
links to <a href="https://github.com/candu">Github</a> repos, and algorithm
descriptions. I’ll assume familiarity with programming and mathematics, or
at least a willingness to learn.</li>
</ul>

<p>In addition, many of my posts will be connected to one or more experiments.
For instance, my upcoming posts on self-tracking to address panic disorder will
fall under the <a href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/panic/" class="category">Panic</a> category.
For every experiment, I’ll attempt to post
content in both the
<a href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/non-technical/" class="category">Non-Technical</a> and
<a href="http://blog.savageevan.com/blog/categories/technical/" class="category">Technical</a> categories.</p>

<p>Of course, I’ll be glad to answer any questions you have, technical or
otherwise!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
